[Music]
this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at se-radio.net
sc radio is brought to you by the ieee
computer society by ieee software
magazine
online at computer.org software
need a helping hand with your system's
architecture software mill will help you
design high-throughput back-ends and
event-driven solutions
we're a brand trusted by businesses and
valued by employees due to our remote
first transparent organization which
gives back to the it community through
education and open source
have an idea let's code together meet
our scala java kafka and typescript
engineers at softwaremail.com today
[Music]
for software engineering radio this is
robert blumen
i have with me doug foley doug is a
software engineer at google where he is
the tech lead for grpc
he's active in the open source community
relating to grpc and distributed systems
and is a graduate
of carnegie mellon university doug and i
will be talking about
grpc doug welcome to software
engineering radio
thank you thanks for having me robert
it's great to have you
grpc let's start out with what does it
stand for
okay sure so the rpc part stands for
remote procedure call
which is essentially a way of saying
that a process on one computer is able
to
make a remote call to another piece of
software running on another
computer the g part of grpc is
actually there is no formal definition
for what it means
so it's a little bit of a gimmick every
time we do a release
we will choose a different a different
name that it stands for
so like the version 1.0 release the g
and grpc stood for grpc
one might have guessed it stood for
google but that's not the case
right no that's that's not the case that
is a pretty
easy assumption to make but no even
though it was started by google
grpc was contributed to the cncf
and so it is not actually owned by
google
i want to focus on the rpc part for a
bit
and then we'll talk more specifically
about what makes grpc
different why would an application want
to make an rpc
the most typical reason why you'd want
to use rpcs
is if you had sort of a microservice
architecture for your for your
application
so the way that would work is you sort
of break
break up your application into smaller
pieces that
each perform different tasks and then
these would run
like in a cloud-like environment and
then the rpcs would enable these
different components to communicate
programmers who listen to this in our
audience are familiar with
procedure calls you can hardly write a
program without knowing what procedure
call is
what are the major differences between a
procedure call you make
within the same programming language and
a remote procedure call so i think the
biggest difference there would be
just the fact that if you're running on
a remote system
there's an extra you know component of
the network
in the way and so networks being
what they are you could potentially
experience a loss of connection
and so you have to be tolerant of that
happening whereas
you know if you're running on the local
machine there's no way that you can
disconnect from yourself
so there are more failure modes that can
occur in an rpc
or as a local procedure call doesn't get
lost on the way
exactly yeah so there's there's an extra
level of complexity there also just
being remote means
you need some extra components in the
system because
just to discover the the destination for
your rpc
means you need to do some kind of name
resolution to look up
the service that you want to talk to and
then you also have other concerns
since you have potentially many
different clients and many different
servers you want to make sure
you're doing the right kind of load
balancing so that you don't
have too many clients hitting a single
backend server
and also you want to make sure that you
have you know fault tolerance
built in so that if your server goes
down that your client has backups that
it can talk to
so yeah none of these would apply really
if you're on the same system
i understand many rpc packages work
roughly the same way
could you describe the generic rpc
framework
focusing on common features most
commonly i think you're going to see
a way for a client to connect to a
server
and to send a single rpc
that would consist of a single request
and the response from the server would
be a single response
that's sort of like your baseline
functionality there are other cases
where you can
potentially do streaming rpcs which grpc
supports so the client
and the server are both able to freely
send messages back and forth
but yeah that's that's the basics i want
to
go a bit more into streaming later let's
come back to that
now focusing more on grpc
google had multiple generations of
internal
rpcs of which grpc is the latest one
how are the previous generations
unsatisfactory or
what made it possible and why was grpc
created
yeah that's a great question so yeah
google has gone through a number of
iterations here
and i think in terms of
limitations uh really i think the what
google had as its latest generation was
probably
acceptable in terms of features provided
however
the way that it was implemented was
directly on top of tcp
and it involved you know a lot of a lot
of code in order to
support things that grpc gets natively
through
the advantage of some advances that have
been made
in open source technologies so for
instance http 2
and so when you look at a technology
like stubby which
google uses internally it has all the
features of grpc
and so grpc isn't necessarily superior
because of the features it offers
but it is much more easily brought to an
open source
world it doesn't need to handle all the
streaming cases that stubby handles on
its own
and also it doesn't rely on any other
internal google libraries that would
have made stubby a lot more difficult to
open source
i understand grpc it's leveraging a
considerable amount
of features that are built into http
2 and gets a lot a lot of benefit from
that
go a bit more into what http 2 does and
what does grpc derive
from being a layer on top of that
so http 2 actually does the bulk of the
work
for grpc grpc is essentially
a fairly thin wrapper on top of it to
encode the protocol for grpc
what http 2 brings is a basic
transport layer that is used by grpc
and the features that it has that are
sort of novel versus
http 1 are stream multiplexing so the
ability to have
multiple streams or communications
happening at the same time on a single
connection
and also they provide a flow control
mechanism for managing that
so if a grpc client is talking to some
kind of
back end and it has multiple threads
that are all doing
one or more rpcs to the same backend
then can they all share the same http 2
connection
yes that's right you only need one
connection and the streams are also
all bi-directional meaning the client
server are free to send messages
at any time and so flow control so go a
bit more into the flow control first
start at
what is flow control so flow control is
a part of http 2 that is designed
to prevent a server from
receiving more data than it's ready to
handle and needing to buffer it
so if you think of like a bunch of rpcs
happening at the same time
let's say your server application is
busy processing one
but your client continues to send
messages to the server
not knowing that the server is busy flow
control is that
way for the server to push back and say
wait
don't send anything else on this stream
i can't handle it right now i'm busy
processing the last message you sent
and that the other benefit that that has
is it can block
one stream but the other rpcs that are
happening
on other streams are allowed to continue
because maybe those aren't
stuck because they have different
resources behind them
when you're describing it it's a way to
prevent resources from becoming
saturated
is that more or less correct yeah that's
right it's it's there to protect the
server from becoming overloaded
there's something called head of line
blocking now is that what you're talking
about or is that something different
so head of line blocking i think you can
run into some similar issues
with flow control if not managed
correctly
but yeah so head of line blocking i
think was a http one
problem where a single request
at a time could happen on an http1
connection
this meant that if you needed to request
multiple resources
then you would have to request one wait
to get it back
and then request the next one and so the
http
2 model of uh having multiple streams
at a time sort of gets around that
because now you can make multiple
requests
and then wait for the responses to come
back in whatever order they're ready
i think you touched on this in my
reading about
http 2 or jrpc i mean clarify this is a
http 2 or grpc feature there are three
connection options unary client-side
streaming and server side streaming
what do those mean okay so a
unary rpc is where a client
will communicate with a server so in all
of these models the client initiates the
rpc
and so in a unary rpc the client will
send a single request
and the server will process that do what
it needs to do
and respond with a single response so
that is your
your unary rpc mode this is you know the
most typical
way of thinking about rpcs and then
there are different
streaming options but they all sort of
boil down to the same thing
in terms of you know what it means to
the grpc library but for a user we
expose three concepts we have a client
stream
a server stream and a bi-directional
and so in server streaming this means
that when the client starts the rpc
it sends one request just as it did in
the unary case
but the server will respond with
potentially many different messages
and so it can do this over the course of
you know a few seconds or even hours or
days potentially and so places where you
might use this
are like if the client wanted to do a
database query
it might send the query you know it can
do that in a single short message
but the server needing to return
potentially many many many rows worth of
data
instead of bundling those up into one
huge unit and sending them all
together it could stream the results one
at a time
and that would also give the client the
capability to you know stop the rpc in
the middle and say okay that i got what
i needed
and ended early so the server didn't
need to spend more resources than it
needed to
in order to handle that so that's server
streaming
then there's client streaming which is
the same in reverse
where the client will send mini messages
to the server
the server will wait until all of those
are received it will process it however
it
needs to and then it will respond with a
single
a single message so an example of where
you might use this would be
like if you wanted to upload a file from
the client to the server
then the client might chunk it up into
many smaller pieces
and at the end the server says okay yes
i got it maybe here's the checksum
something like that
the last case is bi-directional
streaming and this is where the client
and server both
interchange messages asynchronously on
both sides
and so here an example of when you might
use this
is a pub sub application where the
client
wants to subscribe to a topic and then
the server needs to send messages back
for that topic
but the client could potentially
subscribe to other topics
or you know it needs the capability of
signaling you know ack i
i have processed this message on this
topic things like that so there's
there's asynchronous communication
happening continuously from both sides
are these then the next generation of
what was formerly
solved with things like long polling
you can definitely uh handle that for
like the server side streaming case
would be a way to
to do essentially a long poll with grpc
would another use case of this be
financial market data where
price ticks are coming in and uh users
seeing updated charts or price data
yeah sure that that would work great for
this so you can get that data up
updated you know asynchronously as it
happens
and does this work for things like voice
listening to music or video streaming
it's definitely not designed for that
there's no
limit in terms of what type of data you
can send you know with appropriate
buffering maybe that would work but this
isn't
you know designed for streaming i am
vaguely aware a lot of that
tends to use udp and not wanting to
incur the overhead of tcp
and the retries right exactly yeah so
you know in those applications you're
more tolerant of
uh data loss whereas you know tcp
and http 2 you get like guaranteed
delivery and so
you know you'd potentially be needing to
rebuffer a lot if you if you tried to
use
something like this for that are you
aware have there been
any layers built on top of grpc that
expose
more of a pub sub abstraction which is
using grpc as a transport but as a
programmer you see it as
pub sub so google has a
pub sub service that we offer in cloud
but yeah in terms of just like a library
on top of grpc
i don't think so there are you know
other things that a pub sub system needs
besides just the transport layer
so really you're looking at like a whole
service i think when you're talking
about
doing pub sub when we're talking about
the
the features provided by http 2 then is
tls
one of those features that grpc can use
so grpc does use tls
we do take advantage of it the way that
our architecture works
you can actually plug in any type of
transport security
and that is negotiated at the beginning
of every connection
and when the client and server then you
know finish that handshake then
what we talk over that encrypted
connection is http 2 regardless of
whether you're using tls or something
else
i did want to mention for our listeners
we had an episode on
http2 which is number 232 and i'll put
that
in the show notes or we covered that
more in depth
another feature of hcp protocols is
caching
is jrpc able to take advantage of that
no so grpc doesn't currently utilize any
http
level caching so anything that you
wanted to cache like that you would need
to do
on the application side okay
you mentioned part of the layering of
the grpc on
that is not built into http 2 is the
encoding
like to go more into that what is what
started
what is the problem it's trying to solve
with encoding
so encoding is essentially the process
of taking
data that you have represented in memory
on the client
and figuring out how to transmit that to
the server application
so you know this is called serializing
typically and so the process here is we
need to be able to serialize your data
to send it over the wire and then on the
receiving side we need to be able to
deserialize it
and be able to you know have it in the
same form that it was at on the client
and how does grpc do that grpc
typically you would use protocol buffers
with grpc which is
a google open source project
it is actually pluggable so you can use
any
encoder that you want with your data and
so we are completely agnostic to that
but sort of
built into grpc is proto support
so if i don't like protobufs i could use
java serialization or anything i want
uh-huh
exactly if you can turn your in-memory
data into
a bunch of bytes and vice versa then you
can use it
why does grpc why was protobuf selected
uh so protobuf is what we use internally
at google
and grpc was started by google engineers
so it was sort of a natural choice
but we also think that it's a really
good choice it is a language agnostic
idl interface definition language that
you can
specify your protocol in and
once you've defined it in that form now
we offer
a variety of compilers to turn that
definition
into something usable for many many
different languages
plus just sort of the structure it has
everything that we need it is what
google is using
internally for our own rpc system stubby
and so you know it already has the
concept of services with methods and the
messages that are sent on them
i believe we have an episode in
development that will come out later
this year
on protobufs and some of the other
packages in that
space so i wanted to focus a little bit
on
the language agnostic part does that
mean i can
call a grpc from for example
java and i could write the endpoint in
python or ruby or whatever is the
favorite programming language of the
team that develops that backend
yes you can so usually the way you would
do that is
the service owner would define their
service they would
specify this is the name of my service
these are the methods it exposes
and for these methods here's the input
here's the output
so the service owner would define that
and then they would publish
that in a protobuf definition file and
then
any client written in any language could
consume that
turn it into a native language grpc
wrapper and use the library for
their language in order to communicate
with that service no matter what the
service was written in
are there client libraries in javascript
that can be used within a browser so
in javascript in the browser is sort of
an interesting
case we do have uh node.js support
but that isn't you know something that
you could run in your web browser
so when you get to a web browser there
are some options if you want to use grpc
on your server there is a project called
grpc gateway
which is a community contribution
that essentially turns your grpc server
into a rest endpoint that your web
browser can access like it would access
any other rest with json endpoint there
is also
a library that is more first party
and that one is called grpc web and
that does involve some javascript that
runs in your browser
that is able to make i believe only
uteri rpcs
to your backend services because it
doesn't really fully support
http 2 right now a while back you said
one of the main use cases for grpc would
be in a
microservices architecture where you
have microservices calling
other microservices it sounds like then
what you're saying would be that
state of the art might be the back end
is communicating among
itself with grpc but what gets exposed
out to the browser is probably
rest or http one something
yeah i mean i think that's that's pretty
typical so yeah if you wanted your
services to be only
grpc then you could use like a grpc
gateway to just be that translation
right at the edge there but yeah you
wouldn't usually talk to your pc
directly to your web browser
as a developer when i'm setting things
up i
find it very convenient to use curl or
postman
to test out http 1
applications is there a curl substitute
in
the http 2 or grpc world
so curl actually does support htv2
it gets a little tricky when you want to
do things like streaming and you want to
try to have an ongoing conversation with
back and forth messages that way
but yeah curl does work with http
too but i you could use curl i guess
with a grpc server because grpc is
using http 2 but you would need to be
able to encode and decode the messages
yourself which is
pretty complicated so instead there are
some applications out there one is
called grp
curl that can essentially provide a
curl-like
experience but for grpc services
i've been going down the trail asking
you some follow-up questions
but if we pop back up to the protobufs
use the term idl and protobuf definition
file are those the same thing yes so the
protobuf
language itself i guess would be the idl
or the interface
definition language so what you would
produce
as a user wanting to create a protobuf
service is you would create a protobuf
definition file
that specifies your service uh using
protobuf
what is in this file so essentially the
contents
are messages which are blocks of data
uh and within your messages you would
have fields
and those could be string fields or
integer fields or other messages
or you know there are maps and arrays
and things like that too
so that describes the data that's
transmitted by
your rpc system then we have
services which are collections
of rpc endpoints provided by that
service
and so the service is essentially a list
of
methods provided and the methods are
inputs and outputs in the form of
messages
hiring a software engineer then we
recommend working with g2i
g2i is the most effective way to
discover talented and pre-vetted
engineers for every project
g2i vets their talent pool through
technical interviews and various code
challenges which are graded by actual
engineers
saving you time and guaranteeing you top
quality through their transparent
grading
they specialize in react react native
and node.js
interested in learning more then go to
g2i.co
[Music]
the use of protobuf ensure strong typing
yes protobuf supports strong typing now
protobuf as you described it is an
independent
tool if i'm just using proto above by
itself then
what do i do with this idl
yeah um you can use protobuf by itself
for some other reasons besides rpcs if
you wanted to
um the thing that wouldn't probably make
sense is the services part
but the messages would still apply to
you in
any world and so what the messages gives
you is the ability to do that
serialization and deserialization that
we talked about earlier
and now you can convert you know
in-memory data
into something that can be potentially
written to disk
or sent over the network in other ways
and then consumed later on a receiving
side
potentially in a different language as
we as we also mentioned
yeah okay what i'm trying to get at so
i'm i'm
doing something with python i have heard
about i compile it down into python
or what what's the workflow developer
workflow
okay right so there is a protobuf tool
that ships with the main protobuf
libraries
that is called protoc and the c there
stands for compiler
and essentially what that does is that
parses the protobuf
definition input and it provides an
intermediate output for
a plugin to consume that plugin
is also provided by google through the
open source
projects and that plugin will convert
that intermediate language into a native
language specific wrapper that defines
the types
and those types of things all locally
for that language
so then you end up with like for
instance a header file in c
that defines your your data structures
this could differ based on the language
because
some languages support standalone
interfaces and some don't
even modifying generated code or are you
just implementing some kind of interface
that is defined in generated code
yeah so the way protobuf works is it
generates the files
and the user should not touch those
except to regenerate them later in order
to
pick up changes in the protobuf file
everything else that's done
is written on top of that so for the
data types obviously you just
define your you know your in-memory
variable
as of that data type and you access it
that way
for services it's a little different but
typically there you're going to
implement methods in order to satisfy an
interface
and then uh you will now have a service
implementation that is compatible with
grpc
okay so you generate this code you write
a
client to send the rpc
serialize it through protobufs sends it
across the wire
other site deserializes and then
dispatches it
through this interface to the method you
implemented that then receives
the values in its own native types for
that language
is that pretty much how it goes that's
exactly right and the important thing to
note is that
most of those steps you just said are
handled by grpc itself
and so the application doesn't have to
worry about the serializing and the
deserializing
if you wanted to use like a different
plug-in to do your serialization you
might need to do some extra work but
typically if you use things out of the
box it becomes a very very simple
development process to start with grpc
you make your proto you implement your
interfaces and then everything looks
you know very very natural to your
language and you don't have to worry
about a lot of those details
we discussed briefly javascript what
languages are well supported
and battle-hardened implementations
yeah so we have a native implementations
of grpc
in c java go and now
csharp.net implementation
but there are a lot of languages
supported and the way that works
is by wrapping the c implementation
and so we have you know c plus we have
python
ruby objective c php
and i forgot to mention we now have a
node
version of grpc that is also native
cool we now
covered quite a bit about that protobuf
i want to move on
talking more at that next level of this
stack
in our earlier discussion about rpc
and local procedure call being different
we are discussing the failure modes due
to the network
with http you get a http
status code which might be uh 4xx or
5xxx when something goes wrong
does a client have any visibility into
that
http status or what does the client see
when the method
fails at the http level so
in grpc we completely abstract away
the http uh transport details there
so the client wouldn't be able to get
access to that
we would provide that in sort of a
debugging way if something
bad on the connection were to happen
like that but
typically the application for grpc would
see
grpc status codes and so if the
connection dies you might see
unavailable for instance as a status
code returned to you
so as a developer many applications do
look at that status code either within
the client
or you have proxies that are going to
retry on a 5.0 but not on a 404.
are you making uh it more difficult for
applications
to take some reasonable steps based on
the http status value
no we see it as trying to make the life
of the developer easier
because they don't have to think about
those things so we
we will translate the http status codes
into
something appropriate for the
application that is speaking grpc
and then you know if unavailable is
something you would like to
have your application retry on then that
that is something that you would do at
that time
knowing the exact http 2 error code
shouldn't be required because
we as the you know the ones using the
transport should be handling that for
the application
can you route grpc through http proxies
yeah so any l7 http 2
proxy should work as long as you know it
preserves the
semantics of http 2 correctly
and then also there are the you know
more tcp level proxies that will work
because they just pass
you know arbitrary data through reading
about this
i understand clients can use either sync
or
async coding model what do those look
like
yeah this one depends on the language
that you're implementing in
so for instance go which is the language
that i work on
there is no asynchronous api for rpcs
everything in go typically is blocking
and so that's the design model that we
followed
with grpc but in languages where
threading is more of a concern
asynchronous becomes very important so c
plus plus and java
need to go through some amount of extra
effort in order to
manage uh the threads because you may
potentially have you know hundreds of
threads available
but thousands of rpcs that you want to
be able to handle at any time
and so you need to be able to do that
efficiently so
the way that you would do that is you
would start an rpc
and then you would provide a callback
that grpc would call
when messages are received for instance
for the developer tool
kit what are the the command line tools
or
building blocks that grpc provides what
are the steps a developer goes through
to get there
to uh client and server up and running
yeah i mean so the first thing you would
do if you wanted to start from scratch
on an rpc service
is you would start at the protobuf level
you would make sure that you downloaded
the
proto-c tool which is a command line
binary for
converting your protobuf into a language
stub
and then you would also download the
plugin for your language
you would define the protobuf definition
for your service
you would run the protobuf compiler that
would produce
language bindings and now you're ready
to develop your application
so you would you would write your
application using that library that was
produced
by the protobuf compiler and then at
that point you would just compile it and
run it
and everything should work so managing
complex distributed system do client and
server necessarily have to be deployed
at the same time or is there some
if if there are changes to the idl is
there some ability
for uh service to be forgiving of client
version
mismatches or vice versa right yeah so
so this is a really huge topic actually
um
you talk about wanting to make a change
to your api
this is you know something that needs to
be done with a lot of consideration
typically the way this works is you make
sure that the changes you're making
are backward compatible meaning that if
you have any existing clients in the
world
that are using an old version but
they're trying to
talk to a server that's written with the
new version
that things will continue to work for
them as expected
so you can't do something for instance
like delete a field
if there might be a client out there
using that field
because now your servers wouldn't be
able to handle it and your clients
would not be getting the results they
wanted so you would make sure that your
your changes are backward compatible the
next step would be to
upgrade all your servers and deploy
those so that they all support
the new features that you've added and
then at that time it would be safe to
start upgrading your clients because now
any server that they connected to would
have that new version
supported so does it work where
the server will say here are client
versions that i will
accept here's a list of versions or is
it more dynamic or it's as i expected
to get x y and z and i see x y and z
coming in so
i'm good right within grpc there's no
versioning support natively or protobuf
for that matter
so any kind of versioning you wanted to
do you would have to do that
manually there is sort of one exception
to that which is
it is good practice to use version
numbers
in your protobuf package names and this
allows you to
essentially release a major version that
breaks compatibility
so you can delete fields and things at
that time
without impacting uh any clients or
servers using the previous major version
so that would be your route if you did
want to break compatibility for whatever
reason
you would do that through a major
version change which you do through the
protobuf package name
but otherwise there's no versions in
grpc
messages will be serialized according to
the version
that the client has and then they will
be deserialized according to the
server's version
and as long as all the fields that it
thinks it needs are present then it will
you know process the rpc if this
process goes horribly wrong do i get an
error message like
deserialization failed could not find
value of x
actually no i don't think that so it
could happen if you change the type of a
field for instance you might get a type
mismatch error
but if you deleted a field actually what
you would see
is a unknown field and the protobuf
deserializer on the receiving side would
see those fields and it would know their
types but it wouldn't
expose them in a language native way
except through like a reflection kind of
interface
i want to move on and talk about
comparison
to rest so in the rest world you have
the four
http methods whereas grpc you have
methods that you define is that really
different or is it just a slightly
different way of looking at the same
thing
yeah so rest has rest is like a very
particular
environment where grpc is
really like a lower level building block
conceptually
rest is more like a protocol itself
and so so all of the operations
in rest are essentially unary rpcs
in the grpc world and so
uh when you compare the four different
modes of grpc's
rpcs and the four different operations
in rest they're they're kind of
different things
do you have any data on performance
comparisons between
grpc and the http and json based
systems i
don't know about that direct comparison
we do have
on our website grpc.io we do have
benchmarks that we
maintain but a lot of these things are
actually going to be
application specific and so we have you
know
what we think are representative
benchmarks but you know obviously at the
end of the day you'll want to
you know test these things out for
yourself let's talk about the benchmarks
can you give me any uh example of a
benchmark that has been done and what
was learned
so our typical benchmarks are a little
bit more
micro benchmark focused so we have
benchmarks that are intended to stress
the latency of a single operation so we
put
no load in the system and we see how
fast can we send a single request and
get a response back
all the way through a grpc client and
server application stack
then we have ones that just try to
maximize throughput and how many bytes
can we push through this thing if we
open up you know lots of connections and
do lots of streams on each one
and then we also have a qps one which is
similar
but instead of sending large messages it
sends
as small messages as it can to see how
many
raw messages per second we can handle
so doug if you could look at some of the
benchmarks that have been published give
me one that
stands out to you or that looks
interesting yeah so looking at our
benchmark dashboard
i see qps benchmark which is queries per
second
that are able to be handled by a single
vm this is running in
gce google compute engine and uh it
looks like i'm seeing about 750 000
for the java client so that's 750 000
rpcs happening every second
do you have an idea how it compares to
the json or
http yeah we don't have
we don't have direct comparisons there
sorry okay
all right so moving on a little bit more
about
building a system on top of grpc
there are different ways that
microservices can communicate
if you think of an rpc as something that
blocks and if you're going three levels
deep do you want
everything to block based on the deepest
layer
versus cueing or i just dump something
on a queue
and then come back and say they did the
thing you want and then it happens later
but with async
programming models and multi-threading
it seems like maybe you can really
decouple everything
while using grpc so are those two models
really different or can you just
determine how synchronous or how much
blocking you want
entirely in the grpc stack
yeah so there's a lot of different ways
to uh
go about this kind of problem uh so
if you have a very long-running rpc
you may choose to actually make that an
rpc that essentially
sends a call back so you would
as a client maybe start a process off
with the server but maybe that process
is going to take an hour to complete on
the server
so in that case if you have the client
sitting there waiting an hour for this
thing to happen
and the network dies in the middle now
if the only way the
server could send the result back to the
client was through that connection
then you've just lost it and now
potentially you've lost an hour worth of
work
along with it so typically for things
like that that are very long running
we would recommend a different type of
architecture that
for that than just a single rpc so
one thing you might reach for here is a
pub sub service
where the client instead of making an
rpc to
a server to say here's my request it
instead
publishes a message to a pub sub service
potentially also
over rpc the servers then are able to
receive those out of the pub sub queue
process them
and push their results back and now the
client
can be monitoring that message queue
that the results come back on
in order to find its results we talked
about
the grpc it could conceivably be used to
support a
pub sub model if i'm building a system
and i know i want pub sub
as part of the system would i reach for
grpc or are there other
tools that are better for that and
that's not really what it's
competitive at i think grpc is a
excellent choice for a pub sub type
model the streaming rpc mode that it has
is essentially perfect for pub sub so
the client's able to
subscribe and then as updates happen
asynchronously
it will receive those off of the stream
so it can be a really big part of your
distributed system infrastructure if not
a one-stop shop it does quite a lot
potentially could do quite a lot for you
as just one piece of infrastructure
uh very much so so yeah it is utilized
very very heavily at google
you know we don't use grpc as much
because we already had stubby in place
and such a migration is a huge task but
yeah for for everything we do at google
almost it's rpc is the whole way down
i think i maybe got stuck a little bit
on
the historical idea of procedure call
which
is old school is a really different
thing from pub
sub but if i just forget what the
letters stand for and try to think about
what it does
it can do quite a lot for sure
okay do the grpc
language specific libraries do they play
well with distributed tracing
yeah so we do have uh support built in
to
all of the implementations of grpc
to allow tracing tools to hook in
and do what they need to do and so
typically
what that is is at the start of our pcs
they will
add some kind of a tag into the rpc
headers
and then on the receiving side those
tags will be received
and now your monitoring can can pick
those up uh
in addition as your services
get more and more complicated they're
built out of many many pieces
so to handle a single request from a
sort of user
client you might have a service that
makes requests to other services
and so on and so forth down the chain
and at every level we will propagate
these tags
and be able to consolidate them so you
can trace the entire flow of an rpc
through the system
where are we in the adoption curve who's
using this how popular is it
i think it's still growing a lot right
now
but it is also very widely used already
so
obviously you know google is built
entirely on this already
and as we look more and more into what
smaller startups are doing from the
start they are
adopting this design philosophy we see
you mentioned it has been open sourced
and are all of the community versions of
different languages all open source
yeah so all of all of the languages that
i mentioned before
all open source and you can find them
all
at the grpc github page
do you have a view on do you see
javascript
becoming more on par with these other
languages and the ability
to invoke grpc from browsers i don't
really have any
specific insights into that actually so
i think what that would require is
really good
http 2 library support in
browser and this will be my last
question
is this pretty much mature technology it
does what it does
or do you see big changes in the
pipeline
over the next couple years yes it's it's
definitely a very mature technology
we've been uh ga general availability
for like two or three years now and so
you know it should be rock solid it's
well tested
it's widely adopted in the community
there's a lot of changes in the pipeline
but not
at the sort of rpc message level
these are more at the microservice
management level
and so you you look out and you see what
people are doing while they're
they're building hundreds and hundreds
of different
microservices and now the problem
becomes
how do you deploy these things in the
cloud how do you manage all of these how
do you make sure
they upgrade together how do they
discover one another
all of that and so a lot of the changes
that are coming up are related to that
so you have projects like istio and
envoy for
helping to facilitate the communication
between these microservices
and then something that we're doing now
in grpc itself
is essentially incorporating parts
of the envoy proxy that is part of that
and part of enabling
your service mesh to really get going
we're incorporating these pieces into
grpc
so that users don't have to manage extra
pieces of infrastructure
like the envoy proxy that would
otherwise need to be
you know it's one more application that
you need to manage the life cycle of so
we're building some of that support
straight into grpc
anything about grpc that you think is
important that we haven't covered
i think the biggest parts of grpc
that are the most complicated bits that
we didn't really touch on are related to
what i was just mentioning and
how do you discover the services that
you're trying to talk to
and then how do you manage the traffic
to those back ends so for instance what
kind of load balancing are you doing to
make sure that your
you know your clients are behaving well
in terms of
putting load on the servers and so you
know that's probably another hour-long
conversation there
but yeah otherwise i think we covered
all the all the basics about
making rpcs listeners would like to
find you or see what you're up to where
should they go
so the grpc project uh our website i
mentioned before
is grpc.io our github page is
github.comgrvc
i mainly work on the go project and so
if you're interested in go that's uh
grpc
grpcgo on github and uh
yeah feel free to look us up send us an
issue ask us a question
uh we're always happy to help but yeah
that's the best way to get in touch with
me
doug thank you so much for speaking to
software engineering radio
thank you so much for having me this has
been robert blumen
thank you for listening
[Music]
thanks for listening to sc radio an
educational program brought to you by
ieee software magazine
for more about the podcast including
other episodes visit our website at
se radio.net to provide feedback you can
comment on each episode on the website
or reach us on linkedin
facebook twitter or through our slack
channel at scradio.slack.com
you can also email us at team
sc-radio.net
this and all other episodes of sc radio
is licensed under creative commons
license 2.5
thanks for listening